You have one minute to read the questions before each section.
You will hear the recordings after the beep.
Each recording will play twice.
You
Section 1
I'm joined today by Matthew Piscitelli who has worked as an archaeologist, a university professor, and an explorer for the National Geographic Society.
Welcome Matthew and thank you for being here.
Now my first question for you is this, why should people care about archaeology?
Why should we care about some stones and bones?
I think it's important to study objects from the past, from ancient civilizations, because of the old cliché that we learn about the future by studying the past.
The past is who we are. We learn more about where we come from and it helps us learn more about our identity today.
We need to study those ancient civilizations so we can help prepare for the future.
And archaeology is also important because it inspires curiosity.
People feel a connection to the past when I say, you know, you're walking in the footsteps of ancient people.
Or, this is what it was like to live 5,000 years ago.
I think there's something very interesting about that.
So it's important that we as archaeologists not simply do our excavations, write a report, and then file that away where nobody will read about it.
We need to communicate what we do and the importance of what we do.
We need to ask ourselves, why does what you propose to do really matter?
Who's going to care beyond a few specialists in your field? Are you asking questions that can inform us about humanity, about culture?
Those are all great questions.
Now, I think it's fair to say that when most people think about archaeology, they think about uncovering objects from cultures like ancient Greece, Rome, and Egypt.
Why do you think that is? What is it about societies like these that inspires us so much?
So there are a lot of famous sites in the world, like Stonehenge and the Pyramids of Giza, that people are always excited to learn about.
And there's something charismatic about them. They have been around for thousands of years.
People, not just us today as consumers of media or tourists, but there have been tourists for hundreds of years.
So people have constantly been interested in these sites.
And I think it's from the charisma, the wonder, the awe of these sites.
It's something about archaeology that makes us wonder.
What was it like to live in the past? What was it like to build the pyramids or to build Stonehenge?
What did they mean? Those voices aren't here to talk to us today.
Are there any archaeological sites or ancient cultures you think people should know more about?
When we look at all of the work that our National Geographic explorers are doing all over the world,
we come to realize that the world is a very ancient place, and there are a lot of civilizations out there to be discovered.
Now in some of those places, like in Egypt, there's a long history of study.
Some other places are more like the Wild West, and that we don't know as much.
For example, in Peru we know Machu Picchu. We know some sites along the north coast of Peru, which are very famous.
[silence]
I'm joined today by Matthew Piscitelli, who has worked as an archaeologist, a university professor, and an explorer for the National Geographic Society.
Welcome Matthew, and thank you for being here.
Now my first question for you is this. Why should people care about archaeology?
Why should we care about some stones and bones?
I think it's important to study objects from the past, from ancient civilizations,
because of the old cliché that we learn about the future by studying the past.
The past is who we are. We learn more about where we come from, and it helps us learn more about our identity today.
We need to study those ancient civilizations so we can help prepare for the future.
And archaeology is also important because it inspires curiosity.
People feel a connection to the past when I say, "You know, you're walking in the footsteps of ancient people,"
or "This is what it was like to live 5,000 years ago."
I think there's something very interesting about that.
So it's important that we as archaeologists not simply do our excavations, write a report, and then file that away where nobody will read about it.
We need to communicate what we do and the importance of what we do.
We need to ask ourselves, "Why does what you propose to do really matter?"
Who's going to care beyond a few specialists in your field?
Are you asking questions that can inform us about humanity, about culture?
Those are all great questions.
Now, I think it's fair to say that when most people think about archaeology,
they think about uncovering objects from cultures like ancient Greece, Rome, and Egypt.
Why do you think that is?
What is it about societies like these that inspires us so much?
So there are a lot of famous sites in the world, like Stonehenge and the Pyramids of Giza,
that people are always excited to learn about.
And there's something charismatic about them.
They have been around for thousands of years.
People, not just us today as consumers of media or tourists, but they have been tourists for hundreds of years.
So people have constantly been interested in these sites.
And I think it's from the charisma, the wonder, the awe of these sites.
It's something about archaeology that makes us wonder.
What was it like to live in the past?
What was it like to build the pyramids or to build Stonehenge?
What did they mean?
Those voices aren't here to talk to us today.
Are there any archaeological sites or ancient cultures you think people should know more about?
When we look at all of the work that our National Geographic explorers are doing all over the world,
we come to realize that the world is a very ancient place,
and there are a lot of civilizations out there to be discovered.
Now in some of those places, like in Egypt, there's a long history of study.
Some other places are more like the Wild West, and that we don't know as much.
For example, in Peru we know Machu Picchu.
We know some sites along the north coast of Peru, which are very famous.
But there are some other places that are very famous.
[ Silence ]
Section 2
[ Beep ]
Hi, Serena. How's it going?
Oh, hi, Liam. Everything's fine with me. What's new with you?
Not much. Well, actually, I'm trying to decide where to go to college.
Which colleges are top on your list?
Just three right now. New York University, the University of Southern Maine, and Mount Royal University.
What was the last one? Mount Royal? Where is it?
It's in Calgary, in Canada.
Huh. Don't be offended, but that seems like a pretty random selection of schools.
I mean, I can understand NYU. I'd love to go to college in New York. But why Maine or Calgary?
Because I'd like to get a degree in ecotourism, and there aren't that many colleges that offer it.
Ecotourism? Hmm. You're going to have to tell me what that is.
My parents said the same thing.
Basically, ecotourism tries to make sure travelers have a great experience, but in a way that can preserve nature and benefit local people.
It's about finding a balance between tourism and the environment.
So, it's like, tourists get to visit natural areas without having a negative impact on them? That's pretty cool.
I know, right? I've always loved traveling, so getting a job related to travel is kind of a dream of mine.
And I've heard that ecotourism is a real growth area in the tourism industry right now, so I'm hoping it'll be easy to find a job after I graduate.
And there are so many news stories these days about how humans have damaged the environment, so it seems like the right thing is to try and protect it, you know?
Right. But isn't air travel bad? Traveling by airplane is one of the worst things you can do for the environment.
You're absolutely right, Serena. So, the idea behind ecotourism is to find a compromise.
If people are going to travel somewhere, ecotourism says let's make sure they travel in a way that causes as little damage as possible.
Let's make sure they act in a responsible way when they arrive. Let's make sure they know the harm that humans can do to the landscape.
That sounds good in theory, but how does it work in practice?
Well, I was reading about ecotourism in Madagascar. Apparently there's a national park there called Singi de Bumaraha or something.
It's this amazing landscape, like a forest of sharp rocks. A great tourist destination.
But it's hard for tourists to get there, and they're likely to damage the landscape. It's a pretty fragile place, apparently.
Okay.
So what happened was these ecotourism consultants came in. They did an analysis of the area and selected some regions that were...
Hi Serena. How's it going?
Oh, hi Liam. Everything's fine with me. What's new with you?
Not much. Well, actually, I'm trying to decide where to go to college.
Which colleges are top on your list?
Just three right now. New York University, the University of Southern Maine, and Mount Royal University.
What was the last one? Mount Royal? Where is it?
It's in Calgary, in Canada.
Huh. Don't be offended, but that seems like a pretty random selection of schools.
I mean, I can understand NYU. I'd love to go to college in New York. But why Maine or Calgary?
Because I'd like to get a degree in ecotourism, and there aren't that many colleges that offer it.
Ecotourism? Hmm. You're going to have to tell me what that is.
My parents said the same thing. Basically, ecotourism tries to make sure travelers have a great experience, but in a way that can preserve nature and benefit local people.
It's about finding a balance between tourism and the environment.
So, it's like tourists get to visit natural areas without having a negative impact on them? That's pretty cool.
I know, right? I've always loved traveling, so getting a job related to travel is kind of a dream of mine.
And I've heard that ecotourism is a real growth area in the tourism industry right now, so I'm hoping it'll be easy to find a job after I graduate.
And there are so many news stories these days about how humans have damaged the environment, so it seems like the right thing is to try and protect it, you know?
Right. But isn't air travel bad? Traveling by airplane is one of the worst things you can do for the environment.
You're absolutely right, Serena. So, the idea behind ecotourism is to find a compromise.
If people are going to travel somewhere, ecotourism says, "Let's make sure they travel in a way that causes as little damage as possible."
"Let's make sure they act in a responsible way when they arrive." "Let's make sure they know the harm that humans can do to the landscape."
That sounds good in theory, but how does it work in practice?
Well, I was reading about ecotourism in Madagascar. Apparently, there's a national park there called Singi de Bumaraha or something.
It's this amazing landscape, like a forest of sharp rocks. A great tourist destination.
But it's hard for tourists to get there, and they're likely to damage the landscape. It's a pretty fragile place, apparently.
Okay.
So what happened was these ecotourism consultants came in. They did an analysis of the area and selected some regions that were...
[no audio]